And welcome to another data structure type.
In this video, we are going to learn about the hash tables and we will see its implementations in C
and Java.
And later on, we will solve the exercises related to these data structures that really be to that inside
the university and inside your interview.
So hash tables are one type of data structure.
They are good at storing data and sets made up of keys and values.
If you look at the Java hierarchy map hierarchy, you will see that hash tables implement that map.
OK, so the key value, key value, there is a key and they value you give me the key, I give you the
value.
This is how it works.
It's very similar to the map.
In this case, a name is a key and the sex is that value.
So if you gave me Joe, I will give you a hint that it is male.
OK, so I will give you the value.
This is how it works, so as an example, let's imagine the data in the diagram stored as an array.
This is an array zero, one, two, three, four and five.
And we have these names stored inside these these arrays and have its value.
So the key and the value are in form of an element inside an array.
Let's imagine looking up at an at the fourth.
Index, which is a Ali.
It is female.
So we don't know what number hours box is in the array.
Thus, we need to search in order to an order from the beginning in order to find the alley.
Now, this operation is called Genius Search in the next few days, we'll learn about the linear search
and the binary search, the key off for the data stored in box zero was Joe, which is not at.
The book's number one was not Ali, either books number two, was not Ali's or three.
Also the fourth the key for the data stored in books for matches Ali.
So we are searching for Ali and we have we have searched for it and we have found that the key for the
value add the fourth.
And by extracting its corresponding value, we learned that Ali's sex is female.
So we give you that key Ali and we get that value female f.
In this way, the linear search operation carries a cost proportional to the size of the date.
Because you are learning, we are searching for alien years.
We are making a linear search and going through all the elements.
It takes time to search through data when it is stored in an ashtray, making it unsuitable choice a
hash table, solve this problem.
So how to make a hash table?
We will prepare an array to store some data for convenience, and we will have five boxes in the array.
Now let's store some data when storing data, offered Joe.
We calculate a hash value for that key using the hash function that result obtained in this case is
four nine to eight.
OK.
So we need to make a function when we need to make like to add the function that will give a give for
us with Joe.
This number four two nine two eight.
We start it.
A more detailed explanation of hash table would be in the next video.
Hash function sorry in the next videos.
How to make the hash function and how to convert data into a value of fixed length.
And and so and vice versa.
So.
OK.
So don't worry, just understand this concept and follow me.
Joe, with hash function, well, give us a number for nine today.
This four nine two eight, if we if we look at our array, our table, we have five boxes.
So this in this case, it is modulus, it's mud.
It's mud.
Five, it is of mud.
Five.
Not murderous mode.
OK.
So five here, four nine two eight is mod.
Five would be equal to three.
Also referred as modulus sometimes.
So the hash value.
So it's divided by the number of boxes in that raid to find the remainder.
Okay, this is the modulus.
The operation that funds the remainder of the division is called the MoD's operation, the mother operation
resulted in a value of three.
So we have divided four thousand nine hundred twenty eight over five and it is it will give us nine
hundred twenty eight point six.
This 0.6 is a remainder.
We have multiplied it with five.
It will give me three.
The data are four.
Joe is stored in box number three because we have the result of four nine two eight more modern.
Five is equal to three and we have stored it at the box three of the array to match the result.
This operation will be repeated to store the other data, so we will follow all the steps in the next
elements.
Consider Sue.
Plus, the hash function, it will give us seven to nine one, we will learn how to get these numbers
seven two nine one later on in the next videos.
And after learning about the hashing function, we find the keys hash value and perform the mod operation
at using the number of boxes in that array.
Five.
The result was one, so we stored Sue and its value inside that box number one.
When storing the data of then, we find the key here is equal to four.
So start, we have stored it in the box number for Mel plus hash equal to this number equal to one by
one.
We will try to store it.
But now is starting now.
But Sue has been occupying the box number one.
So what we do, the data of two was already stored there when something like this happens.
Then it gets connected to existing data, as is at least.
So you see guys here we are connecting.
We use as an X-ray, we have used the key value as a map and we are storing that consecutive and that
link at that and linking elements as a list.
So see, guys, how it's complex hash table is complex.
But but but you see this this algorithm, how that algorithm of storing, then numbers that or the elements
that are the same hash, which is one two and now they are linked together.
There are several types of hash tables structured, but the method that used list is called chain method.
We will learn also in the next video about the chain method when storing the data of Ali.
Do we find the key is equal to three?
Joe is in the box three of our day.
So Ali get connected to a list of Joe Bob with hashing equal to three.
So we need to store Bob in the three, the third box.
But we have Joe and Ali, so we get Bob and we connect it to Joe and Ali link and list for this.
OK, let's imagine looking up to dance sex.
OK, so we have stored all the elements, and now we are going to find the value of the sex of that.
Dan is at the last box, which is box number five, three, four three, the next four.
Now we need to search for it in order to find out the books of our day, we are not going off that dance
at a rate that is in.
So we are going to find the element, then we are not going to search all the elements we make the hash
for then.
So then a plus hash is equal one five three nine Modell's five equal to four.
So Ford will give us the data and the key for the data stored in Box four of the array match that.
So therefore, by extracting the corresponding value, we learned that then six is me.
This is their usage and this is the power of hash table.
The hashing hashing will give you a number, this number when you search for it in this specific box
and you will find your data.
Now, let's consider another example if we are searching for Ali.
Ali, so what happens when we look up to Ali's six in order to find out the box of the array Ali is
in?
So we find the key hash keys, the hash value by performing game mode operation on it, using the number
of boxes in the array.
Five.
The result was three.
So Ali has nine one four three models, five is equal to three.
The key for the data stored in box three of the array was Joe, not that.
So what we will do since there is a list, so you see guys at the box number three where there is a
link unless it starts by Joe, but we are going to search for Ali.
So what we will do this.
So there is a linear search performed on the list, starting with the data, Joe, because there is
a link at least here or less, starting from Joe ending with Bob passing through Ali.
So we need to search all these elements to find Ali.
It is inside this link list or not.
We have found Ali at the at the second element of this linked list at box number three.
So only a linear search performed when we found a link.
Atlas data with G.
Ali was found, entities she made by extracting it.
OK.
So you can see by using the hash function, hash tables are able to quickly access data within everyday.
When hash values overlap, lists are used, making it possible to flexibly handle a certain amount of
data when the size of an array used by hash table is too small.
That overlaps increase, making linear searches more predictive.
Prevail.
Conversely, if the array size is too large, there will be many boxes with no data stored in them wasting
memory.
So discretion discretion is needed.
Hash tables with their flexible data storage and fast look up are used in associative arrays of programming
languages.
This was the hash tables and next videos we will learn about the hash tables, how to implement them
and how to create its data structure and how to use them and there and the problems, and we will solve
exercises later on in the exams.
And the real exams of universities and real interview.